Finding Aid for Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament, Washtenaw County Chapter records, 1985-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament, Washtenaw County Chapter records, 1985-1991
Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament. Washtenaw County Chapter.
1.0 linear ft.
89161 Bj 2
Established in 1984, disbanded in 1992, the Washtenaw County chapter of Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament (WAND), was a local women's initiative advocating peaceful alternatives to armed conflict. The group's members sought to accomplish this goal through coalition-building with other peace and justice organizations, education, political action, and promotion of nonviolent conflict resolution. The record group includes meeting agenda and minutes of the Coordinating Committee (the central organizing body) and subsidiary committees (Executive, Political Action, Strategic Planning). Also included is the WAND newsletter, summaries of member surveys (1985-1987), flyers of special events, and videotapes of protest demonstrations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the organization came from Karen Jania (donor no. 7661 ) in 1989 and from Tobi Hanna-Davies (donor no. 8963 ) in 2001.
The record group is open to research.
The Washtenaw County WAND was formed in December 1984 by two women who attended a speech in Detroit by Dr. Helen Caldicott on the topic of peace and nuclear disarmament. With a core group of approximately 12 individuals, the women sought affiliation with the national WAND organization and helped to arrange a visit of Dr. Caldicott to Ann Arbor in March 1985. Two weeks later, the first formal meeting of WAND was held with 150 people in attendance.
The primary purpose of the organization was to empower women to work towards the elimination of nuclear weapons and to educate themselves and the general public about the dangers of continued weapons production. By 1986, the chapter, now fully organized, worked on many fronts: lobbying, building coalitions with other like-minded individuals and groups, and holding public events and monthly educational presentations.
In addition, the chapter organized a Mother's Day Celebration for Peace in West Park, sponsored an Art Fair booth, gathered 5,000 anti-nuclear petition signatures at the Farmers' Market, sent representatives to national meetings on peace and women's issues, lobbied as defense bills came up in Congress, trained speakers to reach out to community groups on nuclear issues, and brought informed speakers to their meetings.
Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament, Washtenaw County Chapter records include meeting agendas and minutes of the Coordinating Committee (the central organizing body) and subsidiary committees (Executive, Political Action, Strategic Planning). Also included is the WAND newsletter, summaries of member surveys (1985-1987), flyers of special events, and videotapes of protest demonstrations. The WAND records are organized into four series: Administrative Records, Newsletters, Campaign files and Audio and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Nuclear disarmament.; Peace--Societies, etc.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County--Societies and clubs.; Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament. Washtenaw County Chapter (Mich.); Women and peace.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament. Washtenaw County Chapter (Mich.); Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Peace movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Persian Gulf War, 1991--Protest movements.; Women and peace.
Contributors - Videotapes:
Pollack, Lana, 1942-
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records (0.4 linear feet) include by-laws as well as committee reports and meeting minutes.
  - By-Laws (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Committee Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    (includes Executive, Political Action/Strategies, and Strategic Planning Committees)
  - Coordinating Committee Meeting Agenda and Minutes, 1986-1990 (Box 1)
  - Coordinating Committee Retreat Agenda and Summaries, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Speaker's Bureau, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Member Surveys, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Records, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Newsletters, 1985-1991
  The Newsletters (0.2 linear feet) date from 1985 through 1991 are arranged chronologically.
  - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - 1987 (Box 1)
  - 1988 (Box 1)
  - 1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990 (Box 1)
  - 1991 (Box 1)
- Campaigns files
  Folders for Specific Campaigns (0.2 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically by campaign title. Notable is the Coalition Against Weapon Research material dating from 1986 to 1988.
  - Coalition Against Weapon Research, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Peace and Justice Coalition SE Chapter, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Mother's Day for Peace (Box 1)
  - No MX on RR, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Parenting in the Nuclear Age (Box 1)
- Audio and Visual Material
  The Audio and Visual Materials (0.2 linear feet) include an audio cassette of a speech by Dr. Caldicott and 6 videotapes of various protests, speeches and meetings organized by WAND.
  - Audio-cassette
    - Dr. Helen Caldicott at the Cleveland City Club Forum re: testing in New Zealand, undated (Box 1)
  - Videotapes (VHS)
    - Senator Lana Pollack at a WAND Meeting with introductions, 9/25/1988, vhs tape; 33 minutes (Box 1)
    - "Teach-In on the Persian Gulf Crisis" at the University of Michigan Law School with Dr. Ronald Stockton and Dr. Anthony Sullivan speaking on "Regional and Comprehensive Solutions to the Persian Gulf Crisis", 10/16/1990, vhs tape; 2 hours (Box 1)
    - "No War in the Gulf Rally" at the Federal Building, Ann Arbor, MI, 1/12/1991, vhs tape; 60 minutes (Box 1)
    - Bishop Thomas Gumbleton speaking on the "Aftermath of the War in the Gulf" for the St. Mary's Student Parish, Huron Valley Pax Christae, and the Interfaith Council for Peace, 4/3/1991, vhs tape; 1 hour 40 minutes (Box 1)
    - Protests at U of M Commencement during a visit of President Bush, 5/4/1991, vhs tape; 90 minutes (Box 1)
    - "Year of Conscience" featuring Gulf War Noontime Vigil in Ann Arbor, MI featuring interviews with Catherine Strout, Rev. Ann Marie Coleman, Dr. David Bassett, and Jan Wright, 8/21/1991, vhs tape; 27:25 minutes (Box 1)